Hello everyone.
Just came back from a little holiday.
So this is not a normal video,
but I do a Q and A.
I just came back from, Sardinia. Ela was there the week before
to shoot a documentary
about,
heritage clothing
and traditional dress from Sardinia and Romania,
where her family is from.
So added a little holiday, so
that's where we were this week.
I've been pointing today.
My brother's here and a friend,
We just finished the wall, but the work...
That we did today,
Worked on the solar panels as well.
I'll add that in next week's video.
So I did a post,
see what people's questions were.
I do a Q&A once in a while,
but it's been a while, so.
Let's see.
Could you update us on the second cabin?
Yeah.
Ela is cleaning it up right now, actually
to make it her workspace
for the time being.
I have some more work
to do on the workshop,
but I do want to do the roof this summer.
To have that done before winter.
Because working on the roof on
the workshop was quite difficult.
It's doable...
But, clearing
all the snow, it's makes more sense to do something like that in the in the summer.
So I think in a few weeks,
I will start there again.
I made a start there with the bathroom
work.
Last year and in the winter,
when I was waiting for the paperwork
to be finished for the workshop at once,
When that was all done.
The priority was
to get the workshop finished.
And we get there slowly.
There's still a lot of work
to be done inside.
And I think through winter
it will be easier
to do inside work when the heating is on.
You know, and the days are short.
It will be more pleasant to work inside
to finish the workshop.
but it will be great
when the roof is also done for the,
for the second cabin.
Does the tank behind the wood stove work well?
Yeah, it works great, actually.
We're we're fully relying on the on the water
tank behind the stove in the winter.
Now, about six weeks ago,
I looped it through to the electric boiler
because we still make fires,
but they're quite a lot smaller.
So the the water in the tank
doesn't get that hot.
So before it goes,
to the taps, it goes through the electric boiler
where it's heated up to full.
And it works really well.
But most of the winter, I think until late
March, we were using the water tank,
gets up to 60 Cº or so,
really, depending on how big
we make the fires. And,
Yeah, it took a while.
You can see in... well I can't remember
which videos, we were struggling a bit
in the beginning, but now the design is
good and it's working properly.
Why did you decide not to put a skylight in the workshop roof?
It was not approved by planning permission,
so I couldn't put it in there.
It's classified as a garage, basically.
So, Yeah.
It's fine.
There's enough light coming in through
the front door, which are quite big.
If you open those up fully.
And, the other two little windows
and the one in the back, it's light enough.
But obviously
the workshop needs a lot of light,
so there's going to be lights everywhere
above the work tables.
So I'll
be working on that in the coming weeks.
I think I shared a design
some time ago, like an early rendering
of the inside of the workshop.
As I mentioned earlier, it's
going to be like
a little working station in the center
where I do most of the work
with a workbench, table saw
and an outfeed table.
And all around it there will be,
workbenches as well, and storage
all on one level.
I don't think higher cabinet, but things
will be hanging on the wall as well
that I would need on a day to day basis.
Things that are nice to store on the wall,
like hand tools, for example.
But yeah, more
designs and plans I will share later.
And I think the interior work of the
workshop, which is still a lot of work,
if I'm going to make cabinetry by myself,
this is probably a nice winter project to do.
When all the major construction and renovation work is done, what do you envision will be come the main objective of your channel
Yeah, it's a good question.
I don't know.
the question is, when is all the work done?
I can imagine
when both cabins in the workshop is done,
the next thing would be
the front door of the first cabin.
Which is not that good.
I'll redo some jobs.
I'll get into woodworking.
Maybe more painting.
Landscaping, definitely.
Like the.
The primary goal is now
to get the construction work and then the three buildings finished.
But I see there are kind of like five stages in this bigger projects.
The first one being
establishing a livable area,
basically.
So installation of solar panels
and getting electricity and power,
creating taps and the water connection,
which was there, but it was a lot of work to make
it work.
Pipes underground and trenching
and setting up the tent area.
So that was the first
year, half a year or so.
So I had a comfortable situation
with the outdoor kitchen and shower
to live there
and then work on the first cabin,
which is the second project,
finishing the first cabin
and have a permanent living situation
like a comfortable heated space
also in the winter.
That was done after two years
or so, a little bit more maybe.
And then
2nd Cabin is the third project,
and the 4th project being the workshop.
They kind of are coming along simultaneously.
I've done some work on the 2nd cabin, in the basement.
Now the priority is to get the workshop
finished.
And then once all of that is done,
landscaping is the bigger project
for a longer future,
you know, building terrace walls,
stairs, like the stairway
in between the two cabins.
Garden beds in stone,
Making the road better,
Just everything outside.
There's a lot of potential there,
you know, a gate.
Fencing needs to be finished.
There's a lot to do
and to make everything really beautiful,
because it's really messy around the workshop
right now.
it's a construction site,
you know, the soil is all broken up.
Nothing is growing there.
You know, seeding grass and plants.
There's a lot of potential,
I think, there to make the place visually from the outside really beautiful.
Once everything is working inside.
And that could take could take years.
It's kind of an endless job
to maintain the site.
If you want to keep,
keep it looking beautiful, and clean.
You'll be working on it every day.
You mentioned plans to make a pond since there was a natural pond in the landscape. Do you still plan to create terraces and a pond?
Yeah.
A pond, so that is part of that 5th stage, basically
a pond could be beautiful
there.
Yeah, it's in the works.
I mean, I need to spend some time
designing that, but it's really for later.
I think it would be really beautiful
in the gardening area there.
Like in front of the greenhouse
terracing, with garden baths
and a pond could be part of that.
Maybe a duck pond?
Well, it's going to be very dirty.
Ducks could be part
of the animal corner as well.
They need some water, probably
Yeah.
It's far in the future.
How did you come to constructing the workshop without licensed supervision?
No, there is actually supervision.
There's a, director of works,
geometra, architect.
All those people are involved
to legally do this.
You know, they sign off the project,
but they're not in the videos.
What would you say to your 20-year-old self if you cold talk to him?
I don't know...
what was I doing when I was 20 years old?
I was studying graphic design in Eindhoven,
in the south of the Netherlands.
I was playing in bands, writing music.
was doing quite different
things, actually, from what I do now.
Yeah.
I was just on this road...
You just choose as an education.
I mean, you could just...
But you don't know
if that's going to be your life.
But that was the goal
to become a graphic designer.
And no the goal was to become a rock star.
with a band.
Didn't happen.
But there was
what I was at,
actually around 20, 21...
It was the defining part of my life
and career.
I would say I was studying graphic design,
but it was not a great education.
It was fine, but...
I remember I had one good teacher
and he, he really challenged me
and kind of provoked me as well.
I was struggling with him,
but he was actually helping me a lot
and challenging me.
And I think he liked my work.
He was saying, like, you need to...
Because it was the last year of my education
He was saying
you have to work at this design firm
in Amsterdam, it was like a big design firm,
that was based in London
and had offices in Amsterdam and Singapore.
And he said he knew the executive creative
director there.
And he said, like,
I think you fit in perfectly there,
so I'll write him
and then maybe you can get a job there
as your first job after studying design.
And I was very excited about that.
And some time passed
and I asked him a few times,
did you get in touch with them?
And he said, like, yes...
they said, it's
best if you just get in touch with...
with reception or a regular email address
on their website
and just write your portfolio and maybe,
they invite you.
So I did, and actually,
it was pretty random.
You know,
if you are at the start of your career,
you might have a dream
where you could work
and then, yeah, you might have a benchmark
which is quite high up there,
because most of my peers,
that was were finishing
they would go to a local design agency
in the south of the Netherlands,
start there and climb up the ladder,
and then perhaps end up at,
you know, a bigger firm.
but I tried it anyway, trusting
that he would put in a good word for me.
And I had,
I showed my portfolio there
to a creative director,
and eventually they offered me,
sort of internship two-month contract.
Where I worked in the summer there
and it went really well.
And then they offered me
a more longer term contract.
It was very scary.
It was all speaking English.
My English was very bad at the time.
I was 21, and I.
But I asked about this teacher if,
if he did actually some work and
I didn't know him at all, which is funny.
So he he was kind of bluffing.
He was pushing me in a direction.
Okay, Martijn should go there
On my own I would never have done that.
But I'm glad it turned out like that
because it was a
the best first job I could ever have in Amsterdam.
Just as a start,
as a graphic design career.
So I'm very happy with that.
But it was
it was a it's a funny story that
they didn't know him at all.
Have you ever thought about setting up a camera looking out over the valley, or into the woods, in the rain or listening to the river or just hearing the birds and breeze, and letting it record for a few hours?
Yeah, I think it wouldn't work
because that's not how....
How video works, cinema...
Cinema is,
it's a sequence of images
and sound design and a choice
of how long you show something
and what you show, what comes first
and what comes after
I mean, if I could sit here
for half an hour enjoying my time here,
but I wouldn't
just look at the view for that period in time,
you just start looking and then your eyes
go to something else and then you see
a little insect somewhere,
and you look at that and then.
Feel something on your hand.
You scratch your hand
and you figure out that your hands are dry
and your thoughts go there.
And I think it goes all over the place.
And that's because you are here
in this space where there's a lot going on
other than just one camera shot.
I think it's much more, you feel the wind and the temperature.
You smell things.
You can look all around you.
You have this 360 view.
There's a few houses over there.
There's a very deep crevice here.
And this beautiful trees.
So just one shot doesn't work.
I think the videos are,
like a long shot works. My videos are quite slow.
Some shots are 20s, 30s sometimes.
But something needs to happen.
If there will be, like a farmer
with cows coming by through the valley,
and I can have a shot of that,
that could take quite a while.
It's nice to look at that,
but something needs to happen.
A close up of a flower.
You can look it out for 5-10s
and then it gets really boring.
It needs to jump on to something else.
And that's how videos work.
I think it's it's really storytelling.
And, it needs to have a certain rhythm.
It can be a lot faster,
but then it's still every
shot has a different length.
So yeah.
No, I think that doesn't work.
What’s the first project in the workshop once it’s fully up and operational
Well,
probably, the front doors
and the back window,
those are the first things that have to be
made to make it weatherproof.
So I'll probably do that
in the workshop in a few weeks.
And from there it's,
cabinetry and,
shelves and storage in the workshop.
And then simultaneously,
I'll start work also, in the second cabin.
So it's going to be front doors, windows,
kitchen furniture,
flooring I don't know how I'm going to that yet,
all of that
is is more refined carpentry,
that I want to spend more time
on than I did with the first cabin, like
the first cabin was a living situation
I want to be in.
I want to get inside quickly because I was
living in a tent at the time.
And I think with building,
the second cabin is going to be more time
into designing everything,
building it properly, like better....
I've learned a lot too, over the years.
Wood carving, perhaps,
include some of that.
And, I'm really looking forward to that.
And the workshop
is going to be an amazing place to do
these kind of works in it, in a more
professional way, just a higher level
than I and I could achieve before
working at the workbench
outside, outdoors where it is right now.
What’s your approach / philosophy to filming yourself? I’ve noticed how masterful & intentional your sue of lighting is, how much work you put into changing angles, being mindful of focus to draw attention
Well, it's
yeah, it's
quite a simple set up of one camera,
and a drone.
I have more cameras,
but I only use one.
It's just because they break
some time, so I have to  have another one ready.
But I
the great thing of this kind of work is
if you are a creative person
or you make things,
there's always the struggle
to decide for yourself when is something finished?
With a painting, it's like that
with drawing,
But with any work
in making, it's like,
when is it good enough?
And that's a personal choice
for me it's quite straightforward.
It's finished when it's Sunday.
The video needs to be upload
and then it's ready.
So I really enjoy being in this cycle.
of every week making a video,
I try to do it as best as possible,
and it's really just life through my eyes.
I start on Monday.
All the videos are chronological.
I start to work
and depending on the weather, I film
what I experience, what I see.
If the weather is beautiful.
if there’s a beautiful cloud sequence.
I fly up the drone,
I search for beautiful shots,
and that gets mixed
in with the work
that I'm doing at the time.
And that's how it is.
It goes very organically.
I have a very fast workflow, as I'm
saying, with just one camera on a tripod,
sometimes handheld. And,
when I'm shooting,
I also know kind of exactly already how I'm editing it.
And that's because
I've done it so many times
now, this 209 videos.
So it's a fast workflow and whatever I see
and what I find interesting,
what makes me happy
or what makes me feel things, I film that
in a way that I think fits
well for the videos, for other people
to experience, is basically
what I see is always what you see as well.
So yeah.
What happened to the Pajero’s front fender?
Yeah, I had a collision last year,
A while ago already, on the highway.
It was a lot of traffic
and quite hectic at the time. And,
someone was
standing still with their car on the road,
and I didn't see them.
One time I bumped into them.
Nobody got hurt.
It's just a car
wreck got wrecked a bit on the side a bit
So I still have to replace,
those parts and,
but, yeah, you know, it's
always a rough drive here, so that's why
I'm holding back on repairing it.
It gets scratches all the time
here in the forest.
Yeah.
So finishing workshop, roughly,
and then at some point, start building
scaffolding for the second cabin
to do the roof.
That scaffolding is going to be very much
in the way of where we are living.
So that's so that's best
to do the roof in the summer
or the end of the summer
and then before for the snow falls.
That's all done and scaffolding can go away.
That project takes a long time.
If it's done in winter with short daylight
and just cleaning
snow every time, like last winter was not
a it's not a good idea.
It was fine at the time, but I mean...
but so that's next.
And then I come back to the workshop,
probably
in autumn, working on the inside more.
I'm going to build a woodstove in there
or and a chimney pipe
so I can keep it warm and
when the days are very, short coming
winter, work inside and be comfortable.
So yeah, workshop, second cabin.
And then in a year or so,
second cabin, it's going to be
no, it's not going to be finished.
I think it's going to take another
two years to get things really finished up.
But we'll see.
I don't I don't plan these things much,
but I want to I just want
to get the roof done.
And but the first coming weeks
is solar panels finishing
and do the floor of the workshop,
and then probably doors.
It just needs to be waterproof
before I jump onto the roof.